Be careful what you wish for.
Wish is a animation, family, fantasy film directed by Chris Buck.
Asha, a sharp-witted idealist, makes a wish so powerful that it is answered by a
cosmic force – a little ball of boundless energy called Star.
Together, Asha and Star confront a most formidable foe - the ruler of Rosas, King Magnifico - to save her community and prove
that when the will of one courageous human connects with the magic of the stars, wondrous things can happen.
Asha (voice), played by Ariana DeBose.
King Magnifico (voice), played by Chris Pine.
Valentino (voice), played by Alan Tudyk.
Queen Amaya (voice), played by Angelique Cabral.
Sabino (voice), played by Victor Garber.
Sakina (voice), played by Natasha Rothwell.
Wish is a 2023 American animated musical fantasy film
produced by Walt Disney Animation Studios.
It was directed by Chris Buck and Fawn Veerasunthorn and written by Jennifer Lee and Allison Moore, and stars the voices of Ariana DeBose, Chris
Pine, Alan Tudyk, Angelique Cabral, Victor Garber, Natasha Rothwell, Harvey Guillén, Evan Peters, Ramy Youssef, and Jon Rudnitsky.
The story follows a 17-year-old girl named Asha (DeBose), who makes
a passionate plea to the stars in a moment of need.
She meets a living, magic fallen star, and together they face the kingdom
of Rosas's devious ruler, the sorcerer Magnifico (Pine).
Wish is inspired by Disney's centennial, tying together a
theme of most Disney films: wishes coming true.
The film is noted to be the origin story for the "wishing star".
The film's art style combines computer animation with
the look of traditional animation.
Development of Wish began in 2018 but was not publicly disclosed until January 2022, when
it was revealed that Lee was writing an original film at Disney Animation.
In September 2022, the project was officially announced, with the title
revealed alongside the involvement of DeBose and Tudyk.
Buck and Veerasunthorn, who had worked with Lee on Frozen (2013) and Frozen II (2019) as co-director and story artist,
were confirmed as directors the same month, with Moore later hired to join Lee in writing the screenplay.
Julia Michaels and Benjamin Rice wrote the songs, while frequent
Disney orchestrator Dave Metzger composed the score.
Wish premiered at the El Capitan Theatre in Hollywood, Los Angeles, on November 8,
2023, and was theatrically released in the United States on November 22.
The film received mixed reviews and grossed roughly $255 million
worldwide on a production budget of $175–200 million.
Analysts considered it to be a box-office bomb, as the film lost the studio an estimated $131
million after accounting for income from streaming and home entertainment.
On Disney+, it became the third most viewed premiere for a
film from Walt Disney Animation Studios.
The film was nominated for several awards, including the
Golden Globe Award for Best Animated Feature Film.
The film explores themes of friendship, villain, black magic, wish, musical.
The tone is uplifting.